Matthew Vassar, Jr. Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Matthew Vassar, Jr. Collection
1841 – 1880
NPkMC-223-084
0.5 Linear Feet
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Matthew Vassar, Jr.
The collection contains diary excerpts of Matthew Vassar, Jr. printed in the Poughkeepsie Eagle, covering the tumultuous years before the Civil War, during the war, and afterwards. Matthew Vassar details Poughkeepsie history and the countrywide events that influenced Poughkeepsie, during the almost 40 year period of 1841 through 1880. There are also small pamphlets from the 1930s, of Public Officers and Boards in Poughkeepsie and the rules of the Franklin D. Roosevelt Home Club and the Poughkeepsie Police Manual.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of 14 printings of excerpted sections of Matthew Vassar’s diary entries which start in 1841 and end in 1880, printed by the Poughkeepsie Eagle. There are also two pamphlets of Samuel Moore’s from the 1920s and 1930s and the Poughkeepsie Police Manual.
The Collection was donated to Marist College by the Moore Brothers.
Historical Note
Matthew Vassar, Jr., who was born in 1809, was the nephew of Matthew Vassar, who founded Vassar College. Matthew Vassar helped to care for Matthew Vassar, Jr. and his brother John Guy Vassar after their father’s death. Matthew Vassar, Jr. and his brother John were involved in their uncle’s brewing business, becoming partners in the business with their uncle. Both also served as trustees of Vassar College. They were all influential members and philanthropists of the Poughkeepsie community. The brothers both gave funds to finance the construction of the Vassar Brothers Hospital, Laboratory, and The Home for Aged Men. Matthew Vassar, Jr. also donated money to the Baptist Church, of which he was a member, and served as President of Poughkeepsie branch of the center for the prevention of cruelty to animals. He kept a diary detailing the events transpiring in the country and Poughkeepsie between 1841 and 1880, which the Poughkeepsie Eagle reprinted. Matthew Vassar, Jr. died in August of 1881 at the age of 73.
Samuel A. Moore, who donated the collection, lived in Poughkeepsie, N.Y. and served as Police Commissioner in the 1930s.
There are no restrictions on this collection
Arrangement of the Collection
These records are organized into two series: 1) Diary Excerpts and 2) Miscellaneous
Materials retain their original order
- 1. Diary Excerpts, 1; 0.3 linear feet Box: 1 Folder: 1
  There are 14 newspaper printings of the diary excerpts. The diary excerpts span the years from 1841 through 1880. The entries touch on the Gold rush, the building of the railroads, riots, the Fugitive Slave Act, the Civil War years, the death of President Lincoln, and more.
  Original Order
  - Life in Poughkeepsie From 1841 to 1849, 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Life in Poughkeepsie From 1849 to 1851, 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Life in Poughkeepsie in 1860., 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Stirring Events of the First Year of the War. 1861., 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Events in the Second Year of the War. 1862., 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Life in Poughkeepsie From 1851 to 1854, 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Life in Poughkeepsie From 1854 to 1856, 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Events in Poughkeepsie From 1858 to 1860, 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Events in Poughkeepsie During the Last Year of the War., 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Poughkeepsie Events in 1865 and 1866, 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Events in Poughkeepsie During the Busy Years 1867, 1868, 1869, 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Poughkeepsie Events in the Boom Years of 1870 and 1871, 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Life in Poughkeepsie From 1872 to 1875, 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Events in Poughkeepsie From 1875 to June 1880, 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 2. Miscellaneous, 2; 0.2 Linear Foot Box: 2 Folder: 1
  The pamphlet Franklin D. Roosevelt Home Club outlines the club’s Preamble and By- Laws. It was revised in 1931. The other pamphlet lists the City of Poughkeepsie’s Public Officers and Boards of 1938. There is also the Poughkeepsie Police Manual from 1929.
  - Public Officers and Boards. 1938. Poughkeepsie, New York, 15 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Franklin D. Roosevelt Home Club. Preamble and By-Laws. 1931., 16 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Police Manual. Rules and Regulations for the Government of the Department of Police of the City of Poughkeepsie. Poughkeepsie, N.Y. 1929., 17 (Box 2, Folder 1)